英特尔4004，
Intel 4004.
这可是1971年发布的史上第一款正儿八经拿出来卖的微处理器
The Intel 4004, released in 1971, was the first commercial microprocessor in history.
它是个4位处理器，本来是给计算器设计的
It was a 4-bit processor originally designed for calculators,
但它证明了，一个完整的中央处理器可以塞进一小片集成电路里
but it proved that a full central processing unit could fit onto a single integrated circuit
containing just 2,300 transistors and running at 740 kHz.
上面只有区区2300个晶体管，运行频率740kHz
它一次只能处理一条简单的指令
It handled simple instructions one step at a time.
性能虽然菜，但意义那可是划时代的
While limited in performance, its importance was revolutionary.
4004的出现告诉大家，可编程逻辑电路可以取代那些傻瓜式的固定电路
The 4004 showed that programmable logic could replace fixed-purpose electronics,
从此捅开了通用计算新世界的大门
opening the door to general-purpose computing.
英特尔8086
Intel 8086.
这家伙1978年闪亮登场
The Intel 8086 arrived in 1978
带来了x86指令集
and introduced the x86 instruction set,
这玩意儿在接下来的几十年里，简直就是个人电脑世界的武林盟主
which would go on to dominate personal computing for decades.
它是个16位处理器，最初的频率在5到10MHz之间
It was a 16-bit processor with initial clock speeds of 5 to 10 MHz.
它的高光时刻是在1981年
Its breakthrough moment came in 1981
IBM钦点了8086的兄弟版8088，用在了第一台IBM PC上
when IBM selected the 8088, a variant of the 8086, for the original IBM PC.
这个决定，基本上就把整个PC行业死死地绑在了英特尔的x86战车上
That decision effectively locked the entire PC industry onto Intel's x86 architecture.
从那以后，几乎所有的消费级和企业级电脑都得在这个基础上盖楼
From that point forward, nearly all consumer and enterprise machines would build on this foundation,
这让8086成了计算机历史上最有影响力的芯片之一
making the 80861 of the most influential chips in computing history.
英特尔80386
Intel 80386.
1985年发布的这位，是x86家族里第一个32位处理器
The Intel 80386, released in 1985, was the first 32-bit processor in the x86 family.
它能用上高达4GB的内存，跟它的前辈们比，简直是鸟枪换炮
It could address up to 4 gigabytes of memory, a huge leap from its predecessors.
它最大的一个创新叫“保护模式”
One of its biggest innovations was Protected Mode,
能让操作系统把不同软件的内存隔离开
which allowed operating systems to isolate memory between applications,
这样软件之间就不会打架，系统也就不容易崩溃
preventing crashes and improving stability.
这个功能实现了真正的多任务处理，让好几个程序能同时跑，还互不干扰
This feature enabled true multitasking, letting multiple programs run at the same time without interfering with each other.
80386还能跑老前辈们的软件，兼容性这一块
The 80386 was also backwards compatible, meaning it could still run software built for earlier processors.
靠着这些本事，它成了Windows 3.0和Unix这些高级操作系统的基石
With these capabilities, it became the foundation for advanced operating systems like Windows 3.0 and Unix variants,
把个人电脑一脚踹进了现代计算时代
pushing the PC firmly into the modern computing era.
英特尔的入门级处理器，头一个就是赛扬系列
Intel's entry-level processors begin with the Celeron series.
菜羊来喽
赛扬芯片就是为了最最基本的电脑需求设计的
Celeron chips are designed for the most basic computing needs.
它们通常核心数量少，频率也低
They usually feature a small number of cores and relatively low clock speeds,
意思就是，干重活累活是指望不上它了
which means they cannot handle demanding tasks.
一般就是用它上上网，收发个邮件，淘个宝，看个标清或者高清视频
Typical use cases include web browsing, email, online shopping, streaming standard definition,
再或者就是简单编辑个文档啥的
or high-definition video, and light document editing.
你经常能在那些便宜笔记本
You will often find them in budget laptops,
廉价台式机和学校的Chromebook里看到它的身影
low-cost desktops, and school devices, such as Chromebooks.
因为性能实在有限，所以多开几个程序或者玩游戏
Because of their limited performance, they struggle with multitasking, gaming,
又或者用任何需要点计算能力的软件，它都会红温
or any software requiring significant processing power.
它唯一的优点就是便宜
Their main advantage is low-cost.
但对大多数人来说，这性价比，还不如稍微加点钱买个好点的
But for most consumers, they provide poor value compared to slightly more powerful options.
英特尔奔腾
Intel Pentium.
比赛扬高一个档次的就是奔腾系列了
One step above Celeron is the Pentium series.
奔腾处理器在90年代和21世纪初，那可是英特尔的当家花旦
Pentium processors were once Intel's flagship line in the 1990s and early 2000s,
但现在嘛，已经沦落到低端入门级别了
but today they occupy a low-budget tier.
跟赛扬比，它的频率通常更高，核心也更多点
They generally offer higher clock speeds and more cores than Celeron,
所以放视频能更流畅，也能应付一些轻度的多任务
which allows them to handle smoother video playback, light multitasking,
像Word，Excel还有开个视频会议啥的，都还行
and standard office applications such as Word, Excel, and Zoom calls.
玩点小游戏，处理些简单的媒体任务，也比赛扬靠谱
They can manage simple games and media tasks more reliably than Celeron.
奔腾芯片常见于中低价位的笔记本和台式机里
Pentium chips are commonly found in laptops and desktops in the lower mid-range price segment.
想用它畅玩大型游戏，剪视频或者跑专业软件还是别想了
They remain unsuitable for heavy gaming, video editing, or professional applications,
但对于学生党，办公室文员和预算紧张的普通用户来说，体验还算过得去
but they provide an acceptable experience for students, office workers, and general users on a tight budget.
奔腾Pro，奔腾2和奔腾3
Intel Pentium Pro and Pentium 2 and Pentium 3.
The Pentium Pro, released in 1995, was a processor aimed at servers and workstations.
奔腾Pro在1995年发布，是针对服务器和工作站的处理器
它引入了乱序执行技术
It introduced out-of-order execution,
这个功能就是CPU可以自己调整指令的执行顺序
a feature where the CPU could rearrange the order of instructions internally
来让效率最大化，不让自己的计算单元闲着
to maximize efficiency and keep its pipelines busy.
虽然因为它太贵了，在普通人电脑里没火起来
Although not very successful in consumer PCs due to its cost,
但它给英特尔未来的架构铺好了路
it set the stage for Intel's future architectures.
到了1997年，奔腾2把这些高级功能带到了主流台式机上
In 1997, the Pentium 2 brought these advanced features to mainstream desktops.
它被封装在一个很特别的卡带里
Packaged in a unique cartridge form factor,
还加入了MMX指令集，专门用来加速多媒体处理
it added MMX instructions designed to speed up multimedia processing
比如放个视频，压个音频什么的
such as video playback and audio compression.
两年后，1999年，英特尔又推出了奔腾3
Two years later, in 1999, Intel followed with the Pentium 3.
它在MMX的基础上又加了SSE，也就是流式SIMD扩展
It expanded on MMX by adding SSE, streaming SIMD extensions,
这让它在3D图形，游戏和科学计算方面性能更上一层楼
improving performance in 3D graphics, games, and scientific applications.
这一家子芯片，共同撑起了90年代末的互联网热潮
Together, these chips powered the late 1990s internet boom,
以及多媒体应用和早期3D游戏的崛起
multimedia applications, and the early rise of 3D gaming.
英特尔奔腾4
Intel Pentium 4.
2000年推出的奔腾4带来了NetBurst微架构
Launched in 2000, the Pentium 4 introduced the netburst microarchitecture.
这架构就是为了冲击超高频率而生的
It was engineered for extremely high clock speeds,
有些型号的频率甚至超过了3GHz，在当时可是破纪录了
with some models surpassing 3 gigahertz, a record at the time.
然而，这种对频率的疯狂追求是有代价的
However, this pursuit of raw frequency came at a cost.
奔腾4功耗巨大
The Pentium 4 consumed large amounts of power,
发热量也高的吓人
generated excessive heat,
而且性能常常还不如隔壁AMD频率更低的速龙处理器
and often performed worse than competing AMD Athlon processors running at lower speed.
虽然在当年的“频率大战”里市场宣传做得飞起
Although marketed heavily as the gigahertz race,
但这个架构的扩展性很差
the architecture scaled poorly,
逼得英特尔在2000年代中期不得不放弃了NetBurst
forcing Intel to abandon netburst in the mid-2000s.
奔腾4如今被铭记为一个商业上很成功，但技术上却是个死胡同的例子
The Pentium 4 is remembered as both a commercial success and a technical dead end,
它告诉我们，光靠堆频率来提升性能是行不通的
highlighting the limitations of relying on clock speed alone for performance gains.
英特尔酷睿i3
Intel Core i3.
酷睿家族的第一个成员是酷睿i3
The first level in the Core lineup is the Core i3.
i3处理器在酷睿家族里算是入门级的
Core i3 processors are considered entry-level within the Core family.
跟奔腾比起来呢
Compared to Pentium,
它的基础频率通常更高
they typically feature higher base clock speeds,
核心也更多
more cores,
多任务处理能力也更强
and better support for multitasking.
根据不同代数
Depending on the generation,
i3芯片可能有2到8个核心
i3 chips may include between two and eight cores.
这让它能同时开好几个网页
This makes them capable of running multiple browser tabs,
跑办公软件
productivity software,
看个在线视频
video streaming,
甚至玩一些不怎么吃配置的游戏
and even some light gaming.
像《我的世界》
Games such as Minecraft,
《英雄联盟》
League of Legends,
或者其他轻量级游戏在i3上跑起来基本没问题
or other lightweight titles generally run smoothly on i3.
但是
However,
想玩现在那些大型游戏或者做专业的创意工作
for demanding modern games or professional creative work,
那性能肯定是不够看的
performance will be limited.
酷睿i3处理器非常适合学生
Core i3 processors are ideal for students,
普通用户
casual users,
还有那些需要电脑在日常工作中快一点，又不想花冤枉钱的上班族
or office workers who need reliable speed for everyday computing without paying for unnecessary power.
英特尔酷睿i5
Intel Core i5.
接下来是酷睿i5
Next is the Core i5,
这是英特尔最受欢迎的中端处理器
Intel's most popular mid-range processor.
对大多数人来说，i5在性能和价格之间找到了完美的平衡点
The i5 strikes the best balance between performance and price for most consumers.
根据代数不同
Depending on the generation,
i5处理器可能有4到14个核心
i5 processors can include 4 to 14 cores,
更高的睿频
higher turbo clock speeds,
而且通常还支持超线程这样的技术
and often support technologies like hyper-threading.
它们非常适合玩游戏
They are well-suited for gaming,
修图
photo editing,
剪辑视频
video editing,
以及其他主流水平的创意工作
and other creative workloads at a mainstream level.
i5芯片能流畅播放4K视频
i5 chips can stream 4K content,
并排运行好几个程序
run multiple applications side-by-side,
如果配上一块不错的显卡
and handle modern games at medium to high settings
还能在中高画质下玩转现在的主流游戏
when paired with a capable GPU.
对大多数家庭和办公室用户来说
For most home and office users,
i5的性能绰绰有余
an i5 provides more than enough performance
用个好几年都没问题
to last several years,
所以它绝对是英特尔产品线里的甜点之选
making it the sweet spot in Intel's lineup.
英特尔酷睿i7
Intel Core i7.
Above the i5 sits the Core i7.
The i7 line is built for users who demand high performance
in both professional and personal computing.
Compared to i5,
在i5之上的是酷睿i7
i7 processors typically include more cores,
i7系列是为那些在专业和个人使用中都追求高性能的用户打造的
up to 20 in recent generations,
和i5相比
along with higher bass and turbo clock speeds.
i7处理器通常有更多的核心
They also feature strong support for hyper-threading
近几代甚至高达20个
and larger cache sizes,
同时基础和睿频频率也更高
which allow them to handle heavy multitasking
它们对超线程的支持也更强
and complex workloads.
缓存也更大
An i7 can run modern AAA games
这让它们能轻松处理繁重的多任务
at high or ultra settings
和复杂的工作负载
when paired with a good graphics card,
只要配块好显卡，i7就能在高画质或极高画质下畅玩3A游戏大作
while also managing tasks like 3D modeling,
同时还能处理像3D建模
advanced coding,
高级编程
machine learning experiments,
机器学习实验
or editing multi-layer 4K video projects.
或者剪辑多轨4K视频项目这样的任务
Because of their performance,
因为性能强劲
they consume more power
它们的功耗也更大
and often reduce laptop battery life
用在笔记本上，续航通常会比i3或i5的型号短
compared to i3 or i5 models.
搭载i7的电脑通常价格不菲
Pricing for i7 systems usually falls in the premium category,
所以最适合那些需要强大计算空间的专业人士
making them most suitable for professionals,
创作者和游戏玩家
creators, and gamers
英特尔酷睿i9
who need significantly more computing headroom.
在英特尔消费级产品线的顶端
Intel Core i9.
就是酷睿i9了
At the very top of Intel's consumer lineup
i9系列就是为了在极端工作负载下提供极致性能而生的
is the Core i9.
现在的i9处理器最多可以有24个核心
The i9 series is designed for maximum performance
结合了处理重活的性能核
across extreme workloads.
和处理后台轻活的能效核
Modern i9 processors can include up to 24 cores,
它的目标用户是发烧友
combining performance cores for demanding tasks
内容创作者以及那些和最耗资源的应用打交道的专业人士
and efficiency cores for lighter background processes.
典型的使用场景包括8K视频剪辑
They are intended for enthusiasts,
复杂的3D渲染
content creators, and professionals
大规模的软件编译
who work with the most resource-intensive applications.
科学模拟
Typical use cases include 8K video editing,
以及运行虚拟机或处理大型数据集
complex 3D rendering,
只要显卡够猛，i9芯片也能在现代游戏里跑出超高的帧率
large-scale software compilation,
但是，它高昂的价格和巨大的功耗
scientific simulations,
意味着对大多数用户来说完全没必要
and running virtual machines or large data sets.
像上上网或者处理办公文档这种日常任务
i9 chips are also capable of delivering
i9用起来和i5或i7根本感觉不到区别
very high frame rates in modern games
这些处理器最适合那一小撮需要绝对顶尖性能的高级用户
when paired with a strong GPU.
英特尔至强
However, their high price and power consumption
英特尔至强处理器从90年代中期开始就和消费级芯片并存了
mean they are not necessary for most users.
它们是专门为服务器，工作站
For general tasks such as browsing or office work,
和企业级计算设计的
an i9 provides no noticeable advantage over an i5 or i7.
和主流处理器不同
These processors are best suited to a small percentage
至强处理器优先考虑的是可靠性，可扩展性
of advanced users who require absolute top-end performance.
以及对一些高级功能的支持
Intel Xeon.
比如ECC内存，也就是纠错码内存
Intel Xeon processors have existed alongside consumer chips
这玩意能防止数据损坏
since the mid-1990s,
至强处理器通常有更多的核心
designed specifically for servers, workstations,
更大的缓存
and enterprise computing.
并且支持在一块主板上装多个CPU
Unlike mainstream processors,
这让它们成为数据中心
Xeons prioritize reliability, scalability,
云基础设施
and support for advanced features
和科学计算负载的理想选择
such as error-correcting code ECC memory,
虽然在个人电脑里不常见
which prevents data corruption.
但它们在那些需要7x24小时不间断运行
Xeons typically have higher core counts,
和大量并行处理的行业里是绝对的霸主
larger cache sizes,
从金融建模到3D渲染农场，都离不开它
and support for multiple CPUs on a single motherboard,
英特尔凌动
making them ideal for data centers,
2008年推出的英特尔凌动处理器
cloud infrastructure,
瞄准的是一个完全不同的市场
and scientific workload.
也就是低功耗的超便携设备
While less common in personal PCs,
凌动芯片把能效放在第一位
they dominate industries that require continuous uptime
为上网本，平板电脑和嵌入式系统提供动力
and heavy parallel processing,
它的小尺寸和低发热
from financial modeling to 3D rendering farms.
让它非常适合那些需要长续航的设备
Intel Atom.
虽然价格便宜又省电
Introduced in 2008,
但跟主流的酷睿处理器比，它的性能弱得可怜
Intel Atom processors targeted a completely different market.
后来，凌动处理器在物联网设备
Low-power, ultra-mobile devices.
网络设备和一些轻量计算任务中找到了自己的位置
Built with energy efficiency as the priority,
但随着消费者对性能的期望越来越高，它也逐渐从主流笔记本电脑中消失了
Atom chips powered netbooks, tablets, and embedded systems.
英特尔Xe，英特尔的Xe架构
Their small size and low-heat output
代表了它现在想在图形和AI加速领域正面硬刚的决心
made them suitable for devices that needed long battery life.
Xe在2020年发布
While inexpensive and efficient,
涵盖了酷睿处理器里的集成显卡
they offered very limited performance
以及用于台式机和笔记本的独立GPU
compared to mainstream core processors.
它的想法就是把英特尔的CPU和GPU设计统一起来
Over time, Atom processors found niches in Internet of Things,
搞一个可扩展的架构
IoT devices, network equipment,
从入门级笔记本电脑
and lightweight computing tasks.
到数据中心的AI加速器，全都能用
But they gradually disappeared from mainstream laptops
11代和12代酷睿处理器里的Xe核显
as consumer expectations for performance increased.
性能比老掉牙的英特尔HD核显强多了
Intel X, Intel's Xe architecture,
不用独立显卡也能支持现在的游戏和创意应用
represents its modern effort
在高端领域
to compete directly in graphics and AI acceleration.
英特尔的锐炫独立显卡就是基于Xe技术的
Announced in 2020,
目标是在游戏和专业工作领域挑战英伟达和AMD
Xe spans integrated graphics inside core processors,
这一步表明英特尔认识到
as well as standalone GPUs for desktops and laptops.
未来的计算不仅要靠CPU
The idea is to unify Intel's CPU and GPU design
还得有强大的图形和并行处理能力
under one scalable architecture,
我做了一个超赞的关于所有CPU架构的视频
capable of serving everything from entry-level laptops
to data center AI accelerators.
Integrated Xe graphics in 11th and 12th gen core processors
offer much better performance than older Intel HD graphics,
supporting modern gaming and creative applications
without requiring a separate graphics card.
On the high end,
Intel's Arc GPUs are based on Xe technology,
aiming to challenge NVIDIA and AMD
in both gaming and professional workloads.
This step signals Intel's recognition
that future computing depends not only on CPUs,
but also on powerful graphics and parallel processing.
I made an awesome video about every CPU architecture,
so don't forget to watch it later, okay?